There's been international condemnation of the self-styled referendums being held in
parts of Ukraine on joining Russia. The G7, the group of seven wealthiest nations, have
called the votes a sham as reports emerged of Russian forces intimidating people to vote.
These are the four areas where voting is being held. They include occupied parts of Luhansk
and Donetsk in the east, Saperizhzhya and Kherson in the south, and cover around 15
percent of Ukraine's territory. Voting is expected to run until Tuesday and the result
seems almost certain to go in Moscow's favour. These pictures, filmed in Russian-occupied
Donetsk, show representatives taking polling cards to people in their own homes. Here,
at least, it's not a secret ballot. Meanwhile, Russia is continuing to mobilise its reserve
troops with the latest. Here's our Russia editor, Steve Rosenberg. It was the moment
the Kremlin tried to show the people still back their president and what he's doing in
Ukraine. Within days, Vladimir Putin is expected to annex a huge swathe of Ukrainian territory.
There's international condemnation, but at home, the official picture is they trust Putin.
Many of the people here, though, didn't trust us. When we asked the simple question,
why have you come to this rally? There was a certain reluctance to answer. But they had
something to say on the subject of mobilisation. The call-up is worrying everyone with relatives
of fighting age, Natalia says. Not Viera. I'd be much happier if my son got wounded
fighting in Ukraine than die of alcoholism here, she says. Fighting is a proper man's
job. This is not a spontaneous display of love for Vladimir Putin and his policies.
It is a highly choreographed affair designed to give the impression that the whole country
is behind the president. A lot of the people we've spoken to here today have been brought
in specially from schools, from factories and other state organisations.
In Ukraine today, in those areas occupied by Russian troops, self-styled referendums
began on joining Russia. The West has denounced the votes as a sham, a smokescreen for annexation
by Moscow. Back in Russia, more goodbyes, more men called up to fight in Ukraine.
There's growing concern here that the scale of mobilisation is far greater than the Kremlin
have let on. Emotions are running high. Why have you taken our sons? A mother is heard
asking this officer. When he tells the audience that his own son isn't eligible for the call-up,
listen to the reaction. For the president, this could become a problem. Vladimir Putin
once promised Russians stability. Now he's sending them to the front line. Persuading
Russians to keep faith in him won't be easy. Steve Rosenberg, BBC News, Moscow.
And now we can talk to our correspondent in Kiev, Hugo Bashega. Hugo, what is the response
in Kiev to these referendums?
The Ukrainians are saying that this is a farce. There's no legal basis for this so-called
referendum. And I think the message has been a similar message that has been coming out
from Western countries, that this is an illegal process that is being used by Moscow as perhaps
a justification for the annexation of parts of Ukraine. I think we all know how this is
going to go. I think there was a poll that was released by Russian state media yesterday
saying that between 80 and 90 per cent of voters in these occupied areas where this
so-called referendum is being held are in favour of joining Russia. So I think it gives
us a sense of what we can expect in terms of the official results of this so-called
referendum. But we're hearing reports from those areas saying that soldiers are going
door to door, forcing people to vote. People are saying that they're being threatened in
those areas. And Ukrainian officials are saying that the population has been banned from leaving
some towns and cities where this vote is taking place. But here in Ukraine, the officials
are saying that this doesn't change anything and that they will continue with their counteroffensive
to retake territory that's now under Russian occupation. So what do they expect to happen
next and whether these referendums could change the course of the conflict? So obviously I
think the fear is that this is going to be used by Moscow as a reason to perhaps step
up their military activity. They could say, well, look, these areas are now part of Russian
territory and we're going to defend them as if they are part of Russia. So I think this
is the main fear. Even though authorities here are dismissing the vote, they say that
things are not going to change. But I think we need to wait to see what Russia is going
to do as a response to this vote. The vote started yesterday. It is being held in areas
in four different regions of the country and the so-called referendum is expected to be
held until Tuesday. So then we are expecting to hear the official results after this vote
then. And this of course is going to backdrop a further mobilisation in Russia. Does Ukraine
see that as a threat? I think the response that I got from a top adviser to President
Zelensky was that this was more a response from Russia to its defeat on the battlefield.
There was a little bit of criticism, especially on state television in Russia. And here the
view is that President Putin had to do something. I think the view here is that it is going
to take a long time for these people to be trained, to receive military training and
equipment. And we're talking about perhaps 90 days between the point of these people
being recruited and the moment they arrive here in Ukraine. So they think that this is
not something that is going to cause a lot of concern for now. But again, they're using
it as another reason to request more military aid from Western partners. And they believe
that this is Russia's response to the defeats on the battlefield.